A Ahsan (HABIB)

J 880-171-306-6403J 880-172-272-7727■ aahsan.ualberta@gmail.com■ h.ahsan@yahoo.com.comImage: habit of the com/aahsan 2022

Summary — I am a professional with unique analytical and problem solving skills who applied them in different phases of the career: Business/Data Analytics, Operation Management, Business Strategic Management System and Project Management, Engineering & Scientific Research, Energy Engineering Management, Environmental Management and mitigation. I also have academic background of a novel research (MEMS) based MSc in Mechanical Engineering from University of Alberta, CANADA

Status Consultant & COO with a Pvt Company **Rep Of** SoundPLAN GmbH, GeoNoise Thailand **Qualif** MSc MecE, University of Alberta CANADA, BSc ME BUET

Affiliation Fellow (IEB), IEEE, ASME, AIAA USA
Pro.Certified IEEE Xplore, Google Scholar
Nationalities Canadaian German Thai Netherlands
worked with Indian Singaporean Chinese Malaysian

Skills

Areas Bz Ops, PMP, BzDev-SMS,IT,SCM,Energy Automation Business Analytics, AI, ML, Data Analytics Electro-Mech HV/LV Power,AutoControl,MPU,HVAC,VRF Languages MATLAB,FORTRAN77,Python,SQL,VB,C++ Design ANSYS,FEMLAB,AutoCAD3D,SoundPLAN
 OpSys SUSE–REDHAT–KALI Linux, Windows
 Standards QMS,EMS,OHSAS,ISO,IEC,ASME,ASHRAE
 Hobby CompCoding,Traveling,Reading,Writing

Areas of Interest

Information Systems Security & Assurance — Cyber Security — Data Science & Analytics — Machine Learning Artificial Intelligence — Statistics & Analytics — Nano-technology — Environmental Engineering Business Operations — Operations Management — Business Analytics — Projects Management — FinTech

Professional Roles

As the Chief Operations Officer [COO]

- Business Operational activities: Oversee day-to-day activities of processes and process owners
- Operational Management: Analyze operations towards process improvement and sustainability of the company
- Financial Tools to play: IS, BS, KPI, NSV, CAPEX, COGS, OPEX, CFS, PAT, BCR, ROI, NPV, etc.
- Strategic problem solver: Operations, Processes, Operational Crisis Management, Leadership
- Establishment of SOPs: Manage procedures and coaching people, Establish policies to culture and vision
- Project Leader: Direct all managerial staff, oversee daily activity /ensure project efficiency
- Financial Controller: Involve in controlling company OPEX, in projects/products cost minimization

As a Consultant

- Advise the board of directors on best technology practices in business strategic planning, decision making, following-up business & sales growth patterns, crisis management, etc. by using business analytics
- Intervene IT dept. to establish ERP and implement of technology tools to run in advanced and proper way
- Groom the process owners to understand business analytics for their better decision making
- Represent the company to customers/foreign stakeholders, specially at critical instances in operations & projects
- Advise and mentor senior managers to practice latest technology in processes with established SOPs
- Attend and advise BOD while initiating new business units, such as Govt. IT and environmental projects, etc.

Career History

Consultant & Chief Operations Officer

EnergyPac Engineering Ltd. /ENERGYPAC

Pick-Power & Engineering Company

HEAD — Operations Excellence Dept. (OpEx) & Projects Coordinator

Sep 2023 — to date

Head of Operations — Chief Operations Officer

Nov 2019 — Aug 2023

Pick-Power & Engineering Company

Jun 2016 — Oct 2019

Operations Head

i-Energy Engineering Services Ltd.

Jan 2014 — May 2016

Head of Segment – (Engineering Services, EnS)

Rahimafrooz Energy Services Ltd., RAHIMAFROOZ Group

Dec 2009 — Dec 2013

Manager — Engineering Services Rahimafrooz Energy Services Ltd. , RAHIMAFROOZ Group	Dec 2008 — Nov 2009
Manager — Projects & Technical Rahimafrooz Batteries Ltd., RAHIMAFROOZ Group	Mar 2006 — Nov 2008
Head of Business Development – Light Engineering Services (Metal parts manufacturing) RAHIMAFROOZ Group with SEDF, WORLD BANK	Jul 2004 — Feb 2006
NSERC Researcher — Micro-Electromechanical Systems University of Alberta, Canada	Jan 2002 — Dec 2003
Production Engineer — Maintenance Engineer	

Professional Development

TCEL & Rahimafrooz Batteries Ltd.

Computer: Ongoing Online Training

- CompTIA Security+ by Mike Meyers, Python programming with Mosh, Artificial Intelligence: "Machine Learning Crash Course with TensorFlow APIs" by Google Hands-on development

Hands-on development

- Leading to develop a PS module of ERP on PHP MySQL, Simulation, modeling and mapping (e.g. MATLAB, SoundPLAN)

Workshop & Presentation

 Rep-meets, workshops, and paper presentation in Canada, Germany, Greece & Thailand Convened symposiums on Environmental Awareness at the Department of Environment (DoE)

Business Analytics

- Business Modeling, Financial Feasibility, Business Crisis Management

Mechanical & Electrical Engineering

- Designing and Simulation with FEMLAB, MATLAB, ANSYS, CATIA V5
- Electrical Power Technology (Medium and High Voltage) and Automation (Microprocessor based controllers, SCADA, Modbus RTU Network System)
- Hands-on training and manufacturing experience of micro-sensors in the Microfabrication Lab (NINT National Institute for Nanotechnology, Alberta) of the University of Alberta

Professional Training & Courses

	Professional Training & Courses
Japan	National Dissemination Program on Energy Management Capacity Building Asian Productivity Organization, APO
Switzerland	Training on ISO9001, Environmental Management Systems & ISO14000 International Standardization Organization (ISO)
BD	Behavioral and Executive development, SENSEI Training (I+10) SENSEI INTERNATIONAL, NY USA
USA	Full Course Completed on Circuits and Electronics 6.002x Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)
BD	Project Management Professional (PMP) Bdjobs Training Center Dhaka
BD	Training on Occupational Health and Safety ISO18000, OH&S Bureau Veritas
BD	Human Resource and Payroll Management Systems Rahimafrooz Group
Sweden	Machine Sound and Vibration Control KTH Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm

Design, Simulation with ANSYS CFX, FEMLAB & Pro-Engineer & CATIA 3D CANADA

Canada University of Alberta

AutoCAD Training on 2D and 3D BD Institute of Engineers, Bangladesh (IEB)

Nov 1999 — Nov 2001

SP8.1 SOFTWARE: Urban Sound Pollution Mapping and Control SoundPLAN Inc., Germany	Germany
Environment Pollution & Control GeoNoise Thailand Co. Ltd, Thailand	Thailand
Thermal Power Plant (60MW), Barge Mounted (2x28MW) Shikalbaha Power Plant, Chittagong	BD
Education	13
University of Alberta (U of A) MSc in Mechanical Engineering (MecE) — MicroElectroMechanical Systems Research: MEMS - Development of a Micro-sensor to Measure Humidity inside the Human Airways	onton AB Canada 2004
Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology — BUET Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering (ME) — Control Systems Project: Mechatronics - Development of an Automatic Feedback Control System	Bangladesh 1999
Dhaka College, Dhaka Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC) in science	Bangladesh 1992
Dhaka Residential Model School — DRMC Secondary School Certificate (SSC) in science	Bangladesh 1990
Teaching & Trainer Experience	
 Numerical Analysis for Engineers Heat & Mass Transfer MATLAB for Engineers AutoCAD 2D & 3D Noise Mapping, Modeling & Control on S 	SoundPLAN
Papers/Publications/Articles	
Department of Environment, Bangladesh (DOE) Proposition for Digital Ambient Noise Monitoring Network System in Bangladesh for Urban Noise Control	2018
Souvenir, DOE Bangladesh on the World Environment Day 2018 Bangladesh, Environment, and the Insidious Sound	2018
The 23 rd International Congress on Sound and Vibration, Athens, Greece An Ultra-Critical Silencing System: Modeling and Implementation of an Energy Efficient Noise Attenuating S	System 2016
IEEE Xplore & The 2003 Intl. Conference on MEMS, NANO & Smart Systems, Banff, Alberta, Canad Development of a Humidity Micro-sensor with Thermal Reset	da 2003
3 rd Alberta Biomedical Engineering Conference, Banff, Alberta, Canada A Multi-sensor Micro-probe to Map Conditions in the Human Airways	2002
The 6 th APM'99 & International Conference on Mechanical Engineering, IEB, Bangladesh Mechatronics - Development of an Automatic Position Control System of a Pitot Tube Across a Fluid Flow Du	act 2000
Honors & Awards	
Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Full funded Research Grant by Natural Sciences and Engineering	2002-2004
Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology — BUET, Dhaka, Bangladesh Technical Scholarship	1994-1999
Dhaka Board, Bangladesh Academic distinction scholarship	1991-1992
Department of Environment, Bangladesh (DOE) Chief Project Proponent on Digital Ambient NMNS for Dhaka City Traffic	Aug 2022
Department of Environment, Bangladesh (DOE)	
	Page 3 of 4

BD

Canada

Training on Supply Chain Management (SCM) Bdjobs Training Center Dhaka

Three phase training courses on Micro-fabrication Manufacturing & Safety NINT — National Institute of Nano Fabrication, Alberta

Souvenir Article Writer on the World Environment Day 2018	Jun 2018
Department of Environment, Bangladesh (DOE) Symposium Convener and Chief Speaker on behalf of SoundPLAN GmbH	Oct 2016
The 2003 International Conference on MEMS, NANO, and Smart Systems, Banff, Alberta, Canada Publication presenter (first author)	Jul 2003
The 3 rd Alberta Biomedical Engineering Conference, Banff, Alberta, Canada <i>Publication presenter (first author)</i>	Nov 2002
International Conference on Mechanical Engineering in the 21st Century, IEB, Dhaka, Bangladesh Publication presenter (first author)	Jan 2000

References

Reference will be available upon request

(AHM Habib Ahsan) Dated: 19 Sep 2024